A Guide to the Elisabeth Scott Bocock Papers, 1928-1985
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Elisabeth Scott Bocock Papers, 1928-1985
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 260
7 linear feet and oversized materials
Elisabeth Scott Bocock
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Special Collections and Archives by the children of Elisabeth Bocock
Biographical/Historical Information
Elisabeth Scott Bocock (1901-1985) was born in Richmond to Mr. and Mrs. Frederic Scott in 1901. A few years later the Scotts built a home at 909 West Franklin Street, a house Mrs. Bocock was to share with the Junior League's Senior Center and later with Virginia Commonwealth University, which used the front of the house first as dormitory space and then for administrative offices.
Mrs. Bocock attended Jennie Ellett's School in Richmond and graduated from St. Timothy's School in Catonsville, Maryland. In 1928 she married John Holmes Bocock, a Richmond lawyer. Shortly after his death in 1958, Mrs. Bocock began coursework at the Pennsylvania School of Horticulture for Women. Over the next ten years she attended several other schools, including Mary Baldwin College and the University of Virginia, before receiving a liberal arts degree from Virginia Commonwealth University. During her lifetime she was recognized by VCU, the Junior League, and the Federated Arts Council for her commitment to the city, its people, and its culture.
Mrs. Bocock herself lent her energies and talents to a variety of causes. She was a founder of the Richmond Symphony, the William Byrd Branch of the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, the Historic Richmond Foundation, the Early Virginia Vehicular Museum, the Hand Workshop, and Richmond-on-the-James. Most prominent were her efforts to preserve Richmond's architecture and historic character. Through her volunteering, her financial contributions, and the individual restorations which she herself undertook, she was largely reponsible for setting in motion the city's agenda for historic preservation. In keeping with her interest in Richmond's past, she collected some 60 horse-drawn carriages which comprised a lendable Vehicular Museum until she gave them to Maymont Foundation in 1977. At her death in 1985 she was busy promoting the downtown revival of a distinctively Richmond vehicle, the electric trolley.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains personal correspondence, diaries, articles, and scrapbooks; architectural plans; and correspondence, minutes, and other information pertaining to organizations that promote historic preservation, the arts, conservation, and the city of Richmond. Nearly all of the material dates from 1958 onward, with the bulk of the collection dating from the 1970's. Several issues of Revitalization News and Historic Richmond Foundation News have been integrated into the Special Collections' Serials and University publications. The entire series of photographs has been removed and may be found in Box 20 of University Photographs RG60.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Materials arranged alphabetically and chronologically therein.
Organization
Series I--Issues and Organizations (n.d. 1936-1985)
Series II-- Personal Material (1928-1985)
Series III--Oversized Material [architectural drawings] (n.d., 1902-1980)
Series IV: Serials (1979-1984)
Series V--Photographs
Contents List
- Issues and Organizations, n.d., 1936-1985
  - Associated Clubs of Va. for Roadside Dev., 1954-1956 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - Associated Clubs of Va. for Roadside Dev. 1957-1963 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Associated Clubs of Va. for Roadside Development: Miscellaneous Articles, n.d., 1939-1956 (Box-folder 1.3)
  - Committee for the Alternative, n.d. (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Committee for the Alternative 1972-1973 (Box-folder 1.5)
  - Committee for the Alternative 1974 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - Committee for the Alternative 1975 (Box-folder 1.7)
  - Committee for the Alternative: Enviromental Reports 1974 (Box-folder 1.8)
  - Conservation 1950-1977 (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Early Virginia Vehicular Museum, n.d., 1962-1965 (Box-folder 2.2)
  - Early Virginia Vehicular Museum 1966 (Box-folder 2.3)
  - Early Virginia Vehicular Museum 1967-1968 (Box-folder 2.4)
  - Early Virginia Vehicular Museum 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2.5)
  - Early Virginia Vehicular Museum 1971-1976 (Box-folder 3.1)
  - Early Virginia Vehicular Museum 1977-1982 (Box-folder 3.2)
  - EVVM: Clippings from Catalogues/Scrapbooks 1966-1974 (Box-folder 3.3)
  - EVVM: Vehicle Information Catalogue, Vol. I no. 2, n.d. (Box-folder 3.4)
  - EVVM: Vehicle Information Catalogue, Vol. II no. 2 1976 (Box-folder 3.5)
  - EVVM: Vehicle Information Catalogue, Vol III, n.d. (Box-folder 3.6)
  - EVVM: Information, n.d., 1968-1982 (Box-folder 4.1)
  - EVVM: Notes and Correspondence from Scrapbook 1967-1978 (Box-folder 4.2)
  - Hand Workshop: Committee Meetings 1974-1976 (Box-folder 4.3)
  - Hand Workshop: Committee Meetings 1977-1978 (Box-folder 4.4)
  - Hand Workshop: Craft Fair 1976-1977 (Box-folder 4.5)
  - Hand Workshop: Financial Statements 1975-1977 (Box-folder 4.6)
  - Hand Workshop: Garden Clubs 1968-1969 (Box-folder 4.7)
  - Hand Workshop: Miscellaneous Letters and Notes 1962-1978 (Box-folder 4.8)
  - Historic Preservation: Clippings and Brochures 1970-1971 (Box-folder 5.1)
  - Historic Preservation: ironfronts 1970-1971 (Box-folder 5.2)
  - Historic Preservation: Miscellaneous 1963-1971 (Box-folder 5.3)
  - Historic Richmond Foundation: Church Hill 1956-1976 (Box-folder 5.4)
  - Historic Richmond Foundation: Clippings 1957-1981 (Box-folder 5.5)
  - HRF: Committee Meetings 1949-1960 (Box-folder 5.6)
  - HRF: Committee Meetings 1961-1969 (Box-folder 5.7)
  - HRF: Committee Meetings 1970-1971 (Box-folder 5.8)
  - HRF: Committee Meetings 1972-1973 (Box-folder 5.9)
  - HRF: Committee Meetings 1974-1980 (Box-folder 6.1)
  - HRF: Committee Meetings 1981 (Box-folder 6.2)
  - HRF: Committee Meetings 1982 (Box-folder 6.3)
  - HRF: Committee Meetings 1983 (Box-folder 6.4)
  - HRF: Committee Meetings 1984 (Box-folder 6.5)
  - HRF: Committee Meetings 1985 (Box-folder 6.6)
  - HRF: Correspondence, n.d., 1956-1961 (Box-folder 6.7)
  - HRF: Correspondence 1962-1965 (Box-folder 6.8)
  - HRF: Correspondence 1968-1973 (Box-folder 7.1)
  - HRF: Correspondence 1974-1980 (Box-folder 7.2)
  - HRF: Correspondence, Notes, n.d., 1981-1984 (Box-folder 7.3)
  - HRF: Formal Reports, n.d., 1975-1986 (Box-folder 7.4)
  - HRF: Pulliam House 1958-1970 (Box-folder 7.5)
  - HRF: 20th Street House 1983-1985 (Box-folder 8.1)
  - HRF: 2515 E. Grace 1969-1972 (Box-folder 8.2)
  - HRF: Widow Tyler House 1965-1985 (Box-folder 8.3)
  - HRF: Woodward House (Captain's House) 1973-1974 (Box-folder 8.4)
  - Latrobe Theatre 1964-1969 (Box-folder 8.5)
  - Maymont Foundation, n.d., 1975-1982 (Box-folder 8.6)
  - Maymont Foundation 1981-1982 (Box-folder 9.1)
  - Maymont Foundation 1983-1985 (Box-folder 9.2)
  - Memorial Foundation 1936-1959 (Box-folder 9.3)
  - Nature Conservancy 1960-1961 (Box-folder 9.4)
  - Richmond Professional Institute 1957 (Box-folder 9.5)
  - Streetcar Feasibility Study 1982 (Box-folder 9.6)
  - Streetcar Feasibility Study 1984 (Box-folder 9.7)
  - Trees/Pollution 1957-1970 (Box-folder 9.8)
  - Trolleys: Blackpool Trolleycar Ltd. 1977-1979 (Box-folder 10.1)
  - Trolleys: Clippings (Local Papers) 1977-1985 (Box-folder 10.2)
  - Trolleys: Correspondence and Information 1976-1980 (Box-folder 10.3)
  - Trolleys: Correspondence and Information 1981 (Box-folder 10.4)
  - Trolleys: Correspondence and Information 1982 (Box-folder 10.5)
  - Trolleys: Correspondence and Information 1983-1985 (Box-folder 10.6)
  - Trolleys: National Reports 1976-1983 (Box-folder 11.1)
  - Urban Transit: National Reports 1971-1974 (Box-folder 11.2)
  - Urban Transit: Richmond 1947 (Box-folder 11.3)
  - VCU Expansion--Oregon Hill 1979-1980 (Box-folder 11.4)
  - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts 1963-1964 (Box-folder 11.5)
- Personal Material 1928-1985
  - Clippings: Personal 1928-1985 (Box-folder 12.1)
  - College Records: Grades, Transcripts, etc. 1958-1970 (Box-folder 12.2)
  - Correspondence 1948-1980 (Box-folder 12.3)
  - Correspondence: Personal 1953-1981 (Box-folder 12.4)
  - Diary: Mary Bocock's African Study Trip 1961 (Box-folder 12.5)
  - Diary: Originals 1958-1959, 1962 (Box-folder 12.6)
  - Election 1952 (Box-folder 12.7)
  - European Trip: Diary and Pictures 1977 (Box-folder 12.8)
  - Family Matters 1950-1966 (Box-folder 12.9)
  - Gardening 1947-1965 (Box-folder 12.10)
  - Goose Chase 1966-1973 (Box-folder 12.11)
  - James River Garden Club 1957-1975 (Box-folder 12.12)
  - Ligon House (2601-3 E. Franklin) 1969-1972 (Box-folder 13.1)
  - Miscellaneous Articles 1946-1960 (Box-folder 13.2)
  - Miscellaneous Articles: Personal, n.d., 1958-1982 (Box-folder 13.3)
  - News Clippings 1969-1985 (Box-folder 13.4)
  - Playbills and Programs 1965-1980 (Box-folder 13.5)
  - Published Work: Vignettes 1981-1983 (Box-folder 13.6)
  - St. Paul's Church 1959-1962 (Box-folder 13.7)
  - Schoolwork 1958-1961 (Box-folder 13.8)
  - Schoolwork 1962 (Box-folder 14.1)
  - Schoolwork 1966-1969 (Box-folder 14.2)
  - Schoolwork 1970 (Box-folder 14.3)
  - Scotland Trip: Diary and Souvenirs 1969 (Box-folder 14.4)
  - Senior Center: 9019 W. Franklin 1959-1968 (Box-folder 14.5)
  - 2300 Club 1963-1968 (Box-folder 14.6)
  - Unpublished Work: Vignettes 1981-1983 (Box-folder 15.1)
  - VCU: 909 W. Franklin 1958-1984 (Box-folder 15.2)
  - Western Trip: Correspondence 1979 (Box-folder 15.3)
  - Western Trip: Maps, Brochures, etc. 1979 (Box-folder 15.4)
  - Yearbook: Jennie Ellett's School 1916 (Box-folder 15.5)
- Oversized Material (architectural drawings) 1902-1980
  - Bottoms Bridge, Va.: Roadside Development 1955
  - Claremont Manor, Surry County, Va, n.d.
  - Goose Chase: Bath House Addiction 1968
  - Hand Workshop: Proposed Breezeway on 24th Street 1966
  - Main-to-James Development Study 1980
  - 909 W. Franklin: F.W. Scott Residence 1907
  - 909 W. Franklin: Remodelling of Rear Wing 1956
  - 909 W. Franklin: Kitchen Wing/Duplex Apartment Plans 1956
  - 909 W. Franklin: Senior Center Staircase 1960
  - Richmond-Petersburg Turnpike: Belvidere Exchange 1956
  - Richmond-Petersburg Turnpike Landscaping Plans 1956
  - Royal Orchard Land Corporation 1975
  - St. John's Church Area, n.d.
  - St. John's Area 1957
  - St. John's Church Area 1964
  - St. John's Church: Adjacent Blocks 1957
  - Stable for F.W. Scott, 909 W. Franklin 1902
  - Trolley Route: Stephen Tarrant's Proposal 1980
  - Trolley Route: Proposal, n.d.
  - 2515 E. Grace Street 1971
  - 2300 E. Broad Street: Alterations 1963
  - 200 Block W. Franklin St., n.d.
  - 200 Block W. Franklin Street: Power Lines 1977
  - Widow Tyler House, n.d.
- Scrapbooks
  - Victorian Vehicles, Horse-Drawn: Scrapbook 1964 (Box 1)
  - Chruch Hill Scrapbook 1956-1968 (Box 2)
- Serials 1979-1984
  - Historic Richmond Foundation News: Annual Report 1979-1980
  - Historic Richmond Foundation News: Spring 1982
  - Historic Richmond Foundation News: Fall 1982
  - Historic Richmond Foundation News: Winter 1982-1983
  - Historic Richmond Foundation News: Summer 1984
  - Historic Richmond Foundation News: Winter 1984
  - Revitalization News: Volume I, Number 1 1983
  - Revitalization News: Volume I, Number 3 1983
  - Revitalization News: Volume II, Number 5 1984
- Photographs
  - Arab Horses
  - Elisabeth S. Bocock: Richmond Times-Dispatch Photos
  - Carriages
  - Carriages: postcards
  - Carriages and Negatives
  - Drive Around Church Hill
  - Family Photos and Cards
  - Goose Chase (Early Virginia Vehicular Museum)
  - Historic Buildings
  - Horse-Drawn Transportation
  - Governor Robb and Carriage
  - Shockoe Bottom Buggy Day
  - Trolleys